<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation anent the Earl of Argyl</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58717</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1661</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6603</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13704286</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13704286</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101475</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58717)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101475)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 848:46)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation anent the Earl of Argyl</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson, printer to His Most Sacred Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Argyll, Archibald Campbell, --  Earl of, 1629-1685.</term>
               <term>Proclamations --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  Scotland --  Edinburgh (Lothian) --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:101475:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <p>C R</p>
                  <p>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</p>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>A PROCLAMATION,<lb/> Anent the Earl of ARGYL.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES,</hi> by the Grace of GOD, King of <hi>Great Britain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith;</signed>
               <salute>To <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap> Macers, or Meſſengers at Arms, Our Sheriffs in that part, conjunctly and ſeverally, ſpecially conſtitute, and to all and ſundry Our good and loving Subjects, Greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Foraſmuch as <hi>Archibald</hi> Earl of <hi>Argyl,</hi> being (for a treaſonable Paper, wherein he had defamed Our Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Laws) found guilty, by the Verdict of an unanimous Jury, of leiſing-making betwixt Us, Our Parliament and People, of reproaching Our Laws, miſ-repreſenting Our Government, and of the crime of High-treaſon in uſurping Our Authority; he was notwithſtanding keeped at large, without any ſuch reſtraints as are uſual to perſons ſo found guilty: And now he having, upon the twentieth day of <hi>December</hi> inſtant eſcaped, adding the breach of priſon to his other crimes, and without waiting for that clemency which he might have relyed more upon, if he had not been conſcious to himſelf of guiltineſſe that required ſuch an eſcape, We have by Our Royal Letter, ordained all execution to be ſiſted, untill We underſtood the nature of his crime; And our Privy Council having, after the Verdict, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed with Us, that notwithſtanding he was found guilty, and that it was uſual for compleating the Proceſs, that ſentence ſhould be once pronounced, that yet We might in Our Clemency, ordain execution to be ſtopped during Our Royal pleaſure. OUR will is herefore, and We charge you ſtraitly and command, that incontinent, theſe Our Letters ſeen, ye paſs to the Mercat-croſſes of <hi>Edinburgh, Strivling, Perth, Dumbartoun,</hi> and other places needful, and thereat, in Our Name and Authority, by open Proclamation, command and charge all Our Sheriffs, Stewarts, Magiſtrates of Our Burghs of Regality and Royalty, and all others in Juriſdiction, to paſſe, purſue, take, apprehend, impriſon and preſent to Juſtice, the perſon of the ſaid <hi>Archibald</hi> Earl of <hi>Argyl,</hi> where ever he can be found within the bounds of their Juriſdictions: And if he happen to flee out of one Juriſdiction into another, that they purſue him within the ſame: And We hereby Require and Command all Our good and loving Subjects, to concur with, aid, fortifie, and aſſiſt our ſaids Magiſtrates in the proſecution of this Our ſervice. And if the ſaid Earl of <hi>Argyl</hi> ſhall happen to flee to Strengths, or Houſes for Refuge, that Our ſaids Magiſtrates and others aſſiſting them, aſſiege and take the ſame in by force of Arms: And if it ſhall happen, that the ſaid Earl of <hi>Argyl,</hi> or any of his Complices (reſiſting to be taken) be killed, mutilate, or ſlain by Our ſaids Officers, or any aſſiſting them, We declare they are hereby indemnified, and ſhall never be brought in queſtion therefore, Civilly nor Criminally, in all time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And farther, that ye, in Our Name and Authority foreſaid, Prohibite and Diſcharge all Our Subjects of this Our Kingdom, to reſſet ſupply, or intercommune with the ſaid Earl, or his Accomplices, or to furniſh him Meat, Drink, Houſe, Harboury, or any other thing neceſſar or comfortable to him, or to tranſport him to, or from Ferries, <hi>under the pain of Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given under Our Signet at <hi>Halyrudehouſe, </hi>
                  <date>the twenty one day of <hi>December,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred and eighty one. And of Our Reign the thirty three Year.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Per Actum Dominorum Secreti Concilij.
<hi>WILL. PATERSON,</hi> Cl. Sti. Concilij.</signed>
               <lb/>
God ſave the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Printed by the Heir of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to His moſt Sacred <hi>Majeſty.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
